<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title><![CDATA[Loïc Faugeron]]></title>
    <link href="/feed/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="/"/>
    <updated>2018-06-15T08:31:22+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://gnugat.github.com</id>
            <author>
            <name><![CDATA[Loïc Faugeron]]></name>            <email><![CDATA[faugeron.loic@gmail.com]]></email>        </author>
        <generator uri="http://sculpin.io/">Sculpin</generator>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[Semantic Versioning]]></title>
            <link href="/2014/12/17/semantic-versioning.html"/>
            <updated>2014-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>/2014/12/17/semantic-versioning.html</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote>
  <p><strong>TL;DR</strong>: A library's public API can be: fully qualified class names,
  object's types, exceptions, method names and arguments.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>When working on a project, every change made to it can possibly break its usage.
Sometimes this is because we introduced a bug, but some other times this is
because the project's usage needed to be changed.</p>

<p>Or did it?</p>

<p>In this article, we will discuss about semantic versioning, and public API.</p>

<h2 id="semantic-versioning">Semantic Versioning</h2>

<p>In order to make the migration between two versions easier for users, we could
use <a href="http://semver.org/">Semantic Versioning</a>, which can be summed up as follow:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Given a version number MAJOR.MINOR.PATCH, increment the:</p>
  
  <ol>
  <li>MAJOR version when you make incompatible API changes</li>
  <li>MINOR version when you add functionality in a backwards-compatible manner</li>
  <li>PATCH version when you make backwards-compatible bug fixes</li>
  </ol>
</blockquote>

<p>The trick is to define a "public API" (what the user actually use) and promise
that we won't break it as long as we don't increment the MAJOR version.</p>

<h2 id="public-api">Public API</h2>

<p>The "public API" will vary between projects:</p>

<ul>
<li>for a CLI tool, it will be the command names, their options and arguments</li>
<li>for a web API, it will be the URLs</li>
<li>for a library, it will be a set of defined classes</li>
</ul>

<p>Let's focus on libraries.</p>

<h2 id="redaktilo-example">Redaktilo example</h2>

<p>When I started the <a href="https://github.com/gnugat/redaktilo">Redaktilo</a> library I
had a lot of decisions to make:</p>

<ul>
<li>what name and responsibility to give to new objects</li>
<li>what names and arguments to give to methods</li>
<li>what exception to throw in case of errors</li>
</ul>

<p>I knew that I could make the wrong choices, which would mean changing names,
types, arguments, etc. Basically, for the developers using the library it would
mean breaking their code.</p>

<h3 id="private-and-public-classes">Private and public classes</h3>

<p>In order to avoid that as much as possible, I've decided to minimize the number
of classes the developers would use: a <code>Text</code> model and an <code>Editor</code> service.
<code>Editor</code> doesn't contain any logic, it relies on several "private" classes to do
the actual job. It's a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Facade_pattern">Facade</a>.</p>

<p>So my public API was the <code>Gnugat\Redaktilo\Editor</code>'s fully qualified classname
(full namespace and the class name), and its methods (name and arguments).</p>

<h3 id="private-class-constructors">Private class constructors</h3>

<p>Later on in the project we've introduced a version that didn't change the
defined public API, but broke the projects that were using Redaktilo: the issue
was that we added a new arguments in a private class's constructor.</p>

<p>Therefore the public API was extended to <strong>every</strong> constructors.</p>

<p>To fix the backward compatibility break, we made this new argument optional.</p>

<h3 id="exceptions">Exceptions</h3>

<p>Some time passed and we've decided to re-organize the project's exceptions:
moving them to their own sub-namespace (<code>Gnugat\Redaktilo\Exception</code>)
and throwing only exceptions we owned.
But by doing so we could potentially break project's using our library.</p>

<p>Hence we extended the public API to exceptions.</p>

<p>To avoid backward compatible breaks we simply duplicated the exceptions:
the new ones in the sub-namespace contain all the logic and inherit from the old
exceptions to get their types.</p>

<h2 id="making-changes-to-the-public-api">Making changes to the public API</h2>

<p>Defining a public API doesn't mean we can't make changes to it:</p>

<ul>
<li>we can add new arguments to methods, by making them optional</li>
<li>we can change a class name and type, by creating a new one and make it extend the old one</li>
<li>we can change a method name, by creating a new one and use it in the old one</li>
<li>we can add a method to an interface, by creating a new interface and make it extend the old one</li>
</ul>

<p>Those changes will introduce deprecations that will be removed only when the
MAJOR version is incremented.</p>

<p>This can be documented directly in the code, using <a href="http://www.phpdoc.org/docs/latest/references/phpdoc/tags/deprecated.html">phpdoc</a>:
use <code>@deprecated &lt;since-version&gt; &lt;what to use instead&gt;</code>.</p>

<p>This can also be described in a migration documentation (e.g. <code>UPGRADE-2.0.md</code>).</p>

<h2 id="avoid-complete-rewrites">Avoid complete rewrites</h2>

<p>Semantic versioning only applies to versions greater than <code>1.0.0</code>: if you tag your project as
being in version <code>0.MINOR.PATCH</code> you are allowed to break everything. But
remember that it will make your project very unstable, and people won't trust
it.</p>

<p>In theory you could break everything again when incrementing the MAJOR version
(e.g. from version 1 to version 2), but this won't be appealing at all for
people that already use your project. Try to make as few changes as possible,
document them and give time to your users to stop using deprecated stuff.</p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>

<p>Semantic versioning is a versioning methodology which has its perks and
advantages. It gives high priority to user's experience, so you have to define a
line between what should be used (public API) and what shouldn't (private).</p>

<p>Changes to the public API can be made by keeping the old stuff and document it
as deprecated.</p>

<p>When creating a library, remember that exceptions and all constructors (even of
private classes) are part of the public API.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Note</strong>: Many thanks to <a href="http://loickpiera.com/">Loïck Piera</a> and his help,
  without him I'd still think that declaring a class as being part of the public
  API is sufficient.</p>
</blockquote>
]]></content>
        </entry>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[Keep It Simple and Git]]></title>
            <link href="/2014/12/10/keep-it-simple-and-git.html"/>
            <updated>2014-12-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>/2014/12/10/keep-it-simple-and-git.html</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote>
  <p><strong>TL;DR</strong>: Branch only from master, merge back when done and immediately deploy.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Git proposes a branch system with the possibility to merge them together,
allowing you to separate released code from work in progress one.</p>

<p>Git flows have been created to help you keep the same process in your team.
In this article, we'll have a look at <a href="https://github.com/jbenet">@jbenet</a>'s
<a href="https://gist.github.com/jbenet/ee6c9ac48068889b0912">simple git branching model</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <ol>
  <li><code>master</code> must always be deployable.</li>
  <li><strong>all changes</strong> are made through feature branches (pull-request + merge)</li>
  <li>rebase to avoid/resolve conflicts; merge in to <code>master</code></li>
  </ol>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="working-on-a-change">Working on a change</h2>

<p>Changes can be new features, bug fixes, enhancements. They're all coming from
master:</p>

<pre><code class="bash">git checkout master
git checkout -b my-changes
</code></pre>

<h2 id="making-the-change-ready">Making the change ready</h2>

<p>Once you're happy with your branch, you need to update it with the last changes
from master:</p>

<pre><code class="bash">git checkout master
git pull --rebase
git checkout my-changes
git rebase master
git push -fu origin my-changes
</code></pre>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Note</strong>: <code>rebase</code> will rewrite your commits, their dates will be changed
  (therefore their hash will be changed).</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Check your tests, the coding standards and ask for a code review.</p>

<h3 id="managing-conflicts">Managing conflicts</h3>

<p>You can list conflicts (if any):</p>

<pre><code class="bash">git status
</code></pre>

<p>Edit your files and then mark them as solved:</p>

<pre><code class="bash">git add &lt;file&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>When all conflicted files have been resolved, you can continue:</p>

<pre><code class="bash">git rebase --continue
</code></pre>

<h3 id="when-to-merge">When to merge</h3>

<p>Here's a to do list you can use to know if a branch is ready to be merged:</p>

<ul>
<li>is it compliant with the coding standards?</li>
<li>has the code been reviewed?</li>
<li>do the tests pass?</li>
<li>has the Quality Assurance team checked the feature?</li>
<li>will someone be available in the next hour in case of emergency?</li>
<li>does the product owner want this feature now?</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="deploying-the-new-change">Deploying the new change</h2>

<p>If everything is ok with your change, then you can merge it into master:</p>

<pre><code class="bash">git checkout master
git merge --no-ff my-change
git push
git push origin :my-changes
git branch -D my-changes
</code></pre>

<p>It's now time to deploy! You can make a tag:</p>

<pre><code class="bash">git tag -a &lt;version&gt;
git push --tags
</code></pre>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>

<p>Make small changes, release often.</p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[Read it Later]]></title>
            <link href="/2014/11/21/read-it-later.html"/>
            <updated>2014-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>/2014/11/21/read-it-later.html</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote>
  <p><strong>TL;DR</strong>: Use <a href="https://ifttt.com/">IFTTT</a> and <a href="http://getpocket.com/">Pocket</a>
  to read tweets, blogs and stuff later (in a commute, in the loo, anywhere).</p>
</blockquote>

<p>We often find interesting links on the web, but don't have time to read them
immediately. This article will describe how to efficiently manage them so we can
read them later.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>Note</em>: this is an actualization of an article wrote
  <a href="/2014/01/08/technology-scouting.html">ten month ago</a>.</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="pocket">Pocket</h2>

<p>We all have different strategies to "bookmark" links: actually bookmark them,
favorite a tweet, subscribing to a RSS feed... The problem arises when we do all
of those in the same time: wouldn't it be nice to have a single place to read
them all?</p>

<p>We could use our emails for this: we check them often, we can archive them,
favorite them or delete them. <a href="http://www.google.com/inbox/">Inbox</a> from Google
makes the task even easier: we can snooze an email so it only appears at a given
time, or a given location.</p>

<p>The problem is that it mixes "bookmarks" and "notifications": we could
accidently ignore a business email by mistaking it with a "bookmark".</p>

<p>But don't panic! There's an application for this: <a href="http://getpocket.com/">Pocket</a>
(formerly "Read it later").
The advantage of Pocket is that you can install an extension in your browser so
you can save a link or a tweet, and there's a mobile application which works
offline, so you can read in the subway if you want.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Note</strong>: Pocket's ain page is the list of item to read, you can then favorite
  them, tag them, archive them or delete them.</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="if-%22this%22%2C-then-%22that%22">If "this", then "that"</h2>

<p>The Pocket extension allows us to save manually links, but what about RSS feeds?
What if we're used to favorite tweets (habits die hard)?</p>

<p>Well there's an application for this: <a href="https://ifttt.com/">If This Then That</a>.
Basically you can select one of the (many) supported triggers (RSS feed, tweet
favoriting and others), then select one of the (many) supported actions (save to
pocket, send an email and others).</p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>

<p>All the tools are here! They're free of charge and they follow the philosophy
"do one thing and do it well".</p>

<p>I personally store every links to read later in Pocket, either using the browser
extension or with IFTTT using the following recipe templates:</p>

<ul>
<li>If new tweet by specific user, then save in Pocket</li>
<li>If new RSS feed item, then save in Pocket</li>
</ul>

<p>I then read everyting in the subway (no network, but pocket preloads the items
and keeps them available offline).</p>

<p>If you have trouble going back to Pocket, have a look at
<a href="http://geoffrey.io/muna-your-personnal-paperboy.html">Muna</a>: it should soon be
able to send you a digested email of your Pocket's links to read, every morning.</p>

<p>I hope you enjoyed this article, <a href="https://twitter.com/epiloic">tweet me</a> your
questions/comments if you have nay :) .</p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[Pomodoro: manage your breaks, improve your focus]]></title>
            <link href="/2014/04/16/pomodoro-manage-your-breaks-improve-your-focus.html"/>
            <updated>2014-04-16T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
            <id>/2014/04/16/pomodoro-manage-your-breaks-improve-your-focus.html</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="#conclusion">TL;DR: jump to the conclusion</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://pomodorotechnique.com/">The Pomodoro Technique®</a> helps you to manage
your time in order to become more efficient with the following schema:</p>

<ol>
<li>work and focus for 25 minutes</li>
<li>then have a 5 minutes break from your computer</li>
<li>repeat until you've reached 4 work &amp; 3 break sessions</li>
<li>have a 20 minutes break from your computer</li>
</ol>

<p>All you need is a pomodoro timer (I use
<a href="https://launchpad.net/tomate">tomate on Ubuntu</a>), and a strong will to avoid
distractions.</p>

<h2 id="benefits">Benefits</h2>

<p>Breaks have been proven to improve productivity and mental well-being. By taking
them regurarly, you should be fresh from monday morning to friday afternoon!</p>

<h2 id="drawbacks">Drawbacks</h2>

<p>One of the points in the pomodoro technique is to avoid any disturbance. But
when working in a team you cannot ignore your teamates for 25 minutes: what if
they're stucked and need your help?</p>

<h2 id="tips">Tips</h2>

<p>You can use it for any type of work. Just keep in mind that breaks should
completly cut you off from your work: if you're a developer, then you should
walk away from the computer (do some physical exercise, or have a non work
related talk with your colleagues).</p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>

<p>Have 4 work sessions of 25 minutes, interspersed by 3 break sessions of 5
minutes. Then have a 20 minutes break, and start again!</p>

<p>This will help you to stay focused the whole day while preventing burnout.</p>

<p>I hope you found this article interesting. If you have any comments or
questions, don't be shy and drop me line on
<a href="https://twitter.com/epiloic">Twitter</a> ;) .</p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[Technology scouting]]></title>
            <link href="/2014/01/08/technology-scouting.html"/>
            <updated>2014-01-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>/2014/01/08/technology-scouting.html</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Deprecated</strong>: This article has been re-written - see <a href="/2014/11/21/read-it-later.html">Read it Later</a></p>
</blockquote>

<p>As a curious person I'm constantly trying to learn new practices and to discover
tools which might help me, by collecting information via technology scouting and
then reading it.</p>

<p>In this article, I will present how to do so effectively.</p>

<h2 id="collecting-information">Collecting information</h2>

<p>Whenever you find an interesting link, send it to <a href="http://getpocket.com/">Pocket</a>
so you can read it later.</p>

<h3 id="blogs">Blogs</h3>

<p>To find interesting links subscribe to blog RSS feeds using
<a href="https://ifttt.com/">If This Then That</a>: it will send new entries directly to
pocket.</p>

<p>Here are some blogs I personnally follow (caution, they're not really sorted):</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://williamdurand.fr/">William Durand's blog</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.mountaingoatsoftware.com/blog">Mountain Goat Software</a></li>
<li><a href="http://blog.karolsojko.com/">Karol Sójko's blog</a></li>
<li><a href="http://blog.8thlight.com/">8th light</a></li>
<li><a href="http://richardmiller.co.uk/">Richard Miller's blog</a></li>
<li><a href="http://verraes.net/#blog">Mathias Verraes's blog</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.whitewashing.de/">Benjamin Eberlei's blog</a></li>
<li><a href="http://nedroid.com/">Nedroid</a></li>
<li><a href="https://igor.io/">Igor Wiedler's blog</a></li>
</ul>

<h3 id="twitter">Twitter</h3>

<p>You can also use <a href="https://twitter.com/">Twitter</a>:</p>

<ol>
<li>create a private list which will serve as a pool</li>
<li>add any author which might post interresting messages</li>
<li>after a week or so, add the author to a public list</li>
</ol>

<p>The lists only show messages (not retweets) and conversations between people
you follow. They also allow you to create categories.</p>

<p>If you want, you can have a look at
<a href="https://twitter.com/epiloic/lists/">my own public lists</a>.</p>

<h3 id="github">Github</h3>

<p>Last but not least, <a href="https://github.com/">Github</a> can also be a great source of
discoveries: by following someone which stars or watch a lot of projects you
will have them listed on your homepage.</p>

<p>Here's my advice: <a href="https://github.com/pborreli">Pascal Borreli</a> contributes to
many repositories, you should start to follow him.</p>

<h2 id="reading-it">Reading it</h2>

<p>Collecting resources is a thing, getting it read is another one. Just like
<a href="http://verraes.net/2012/12/how-to-read-more-books/">Mathias Verraes advised it</a>,
you should get an e-reader: you can send the pages you gathered on Pocket and
then read them everywhere.</p>

<p>Pocket allows you to remove the articles you found not so interresting after
all, it also allows you to archive the good ones and to favorite the great ones.</p>

<p>Speaking of reading and e-readers, books are another good way of discovering new
things. Do not underestimate them. Here's a list of books I'd recommend:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://git-scm.com/book">Pro Git</a></li>
<li>Clean Code, by Robert C. Martin</li>
<li>Agile Software Development, Principles, Patterns, and Practices, by Robert C. Martin</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>

<p>The point is: current tools won't last and there's a lot of practices you're
not aware of. If you want to improve yourself and keep up with other developers,
you have to try your best to discover new practices (which might be rather old
actually) and new trending tools.</p>

<p>I hope you found this article enjoyable and helpful.</p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
    </feed>